<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>LOCAL Stack Blog</title>
    <description>Software -  &lt;a href='http://stack.inria.fr'&gt;Stack&lt;/a&gt; — for Massively Geo-Distributed Infrastructures</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sat, 20 Oct 2018 16:07:43 +0200</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 20 Oct 2018 16:07:43 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.7.4</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>testing manual post on jekyll</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;this-post-is-a-test&quot;&gt;this post is a TEST&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Evrard-Nil Daillet&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;qsdc12
qsc3
qsd4
cqs5
dc
qsd88
cqsqs8dc
dcqsdc9
qsdcqsd6c
qsdc5
ssqdc5
qqsdcd6cdcqsdcqshhhhhhhhhhhhhhhhhhhhhhhhhhhhhhhhhhhhhhhhhhhhhhhdcsidsqsdcqs4561&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 13 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/publications/2018/10/13/Ajout_manuel_test.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/publications/2018/10/13/Ajout_manuel_test.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>publications</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>One Paper Has Been Accepted to ISPA 2018</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;automatic-energy-efficient-hpc-programming-a-case-study&quot;&gt;Automatic Energy Efficient HPC Programming: A Case Study&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hélène Coullon, Laurent Lefevre, Christian Perez, Issam Rais&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Energy consumption is one of the major challenges of modern datacenters and supercomputers. By applying Green Programming techniques, developers have to iteratively implement and test new versions of their software, thus evaluating the impact of each code version on their energy, power and performance objectives. This approach is manual and can be long, challenging and complicated, especially for High Performance Computing applications. In this paper, we formally introduces the definition of the Code Version Variability (CVV) leverage and present a first approach to automate Green Programming (i.e. CVV usage) by studying the specific use-case of an HPC stencil-based numerical code, used in production. This approach is based on the automatic generation of code versions thanks to a Domain Specific Language (DSL), and on the automatic choice of code version through a set of actors. Moreover, a real case study is introduced and evaluated though a set of benchmarks to show that several trade-offs are introduced by CVV. Finally, different kinds of production scenarios are evaluated through simulation to illustrate possible benefits of applying various actors on top of the CVV automation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.swinflow.org/confs/2018/ispa/&quot;&gt;ISPA 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 10 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/publications/2018/10/10/ispa18.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/publications/2018/10/10/ispa18.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>publications</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Postdoc position</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;18-months-postdoc-position---verdi-project&quot;&gt;18 months postdoc position - VeRDi project&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hélène Coullon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are opening a post-doc position in the VeRDi project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The VeRDi project is funded by the French region Pays De La Loire 
where Nantes is located. VeRDi is an acronym for Verified Reconfiguration
Driven by execution. It aims at addressing distributed software reconfiguration 
in an efficient and verified way&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The postdoc position is part of the multi-disciplinary VeRDi project. 
VeRDi can be divided in two different parts (though strongly related): 
(1) the design of efficient distributed reconfiguration models and systems; 
(2) the formalization of these models and the formal verification of some properties on them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The STACK team and the other actors of the VeRDi project are researchers 
and engineers specialized in the first aspect of the project. 
The role of the postdoc candidate is thus to lead the second research aspect 
of the project with Helene Coullon. To help the candidate in this difficult task, 
two collaborations have already been initiated by Helene Coullon. 
The postdoc candidate will collaborate with the STR team of the LS2N 
specialized in Petri Nets and model checking, as well as with 
the Northern Arizona University (Frederic Loulergue) for aspects related 
to the proof assistant Coq. Moreover, the LS2N also holds the Inria 
research team Gallinette, specialized in proof assistants and involved 
the Coq development team. Finally, research is already ongoing regarding 
the formal and verification aspects of the Madeus deployment model 
designed by the team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This work will be the starting point of the postdoc candidate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The missions of the postdoc candidate are to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;formalize and prove few properties on reconfiguration models both statically and at runtime,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;enrich the team and participate to the team decisions from a formal perspective,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;collaborate with other teams specialized in model checking and proof assistants,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;publish in a top ranked conference.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The expected skills of the candidate are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a strong knowledge on formalization, model checking and proof assistants,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;an ability to collaborate with other domains and to apply their knowledge to other domains,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a strong motivation for the project and its subject.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The postdoc position is based in Nantes at the IMT Atlantique engineering school. The candidate will be a member of the STACK research group
(http://stack.inria.fr/). This team is part of the LS2N laboratory of Nantes, 
and the DAPI department of IMT Atlantique. The salary of the postdoc candidate
will be 33500 with an additional annual bonus of 6.6%. By subtracting taxes 
and spreading the bonus on each month, the net salary is equivalent to 2380e.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please contact Helene Coullon to apply: helene.coullon AT inria.fr&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More details are available here: 
&lt;a href=&quot;http://helene-coullon.fr/download/postdoc-position.pdf&quot;&gt;http://helene-coullon.fr/download/postdoc-position.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 15 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/jobs/2018/09/15/jobverdi.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/jobs/2018/09/15/jobverdi.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>jobs</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Seminar and Collaboration at Northern Arizona University</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;seminar-and-collaboration-at-northern-arizona-university&quot;&gt;Seminar and Collaboration at Northern Arizona University&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hélène Coullon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hélène Coullon has been invited to the Nothern Arizona University from September 10th to 16th for a collaboration in link with the VeRDi project. She has given a seminar the 13th of September entitled “Performance, Software engineering and verification: a wining combination for HPC and Utility computing?”.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 13 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/publications/2018/09/13/NAU.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/publications/2018/09/13/NAU.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>publications</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>VeRDi project accepted</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;verified-reconfiguration-driven-by-execution&quot;&gt;Verified Reconfiguration Driven by Execution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hélène Coullon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The VeRDi project is funded by the French region Pays De La Loire where Nantes is located. VeRDi is an acronym for Verified Reconfiguration Driven by execution. It aims at addressing distributed software  reconfiguration in an efficient and verified way.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 01 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/publications/2018/09/01/Verdi.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/publications/2018/09/01/Verdi.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>publications</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Article accepted by the journal Annals of Telecommunications</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;isolation-in-cloud-computing-infrastructures-new-security-challenges&quot;&gt;Isolation in Cloud Computing Infrastructures: New Security Challenges&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mohammad-Mahdi Bazm, Marc Lacoste, Mario Südholt, Jean-Marc Menaud&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cloud computing infrastructures are highly based on the sharing of
hardware resources among different clients. The infrastructures
leverage virtualization to share physical resources among several
self- contained execution environments like virtual machines and Linux
containers. Isolation is a core security challenge for such
paradigm. It may be threatened through side-channels, created due to
the sharing of physical resources like caches of the processor or by
mechanisms implemented in the virtualization layer. Side-channel
attacks (SCAs) exploit and use such leaky channels to obtain sensitive
data like kernel information. This paper aims to clarify the nature of
this threat for cloud infrastructures. Current SCAs are done locally
and exploit isolation challenges of virtualized environments to
retrieve sensitive information. In this paper, we also clarify the
concept of distributed side-channel attack (DSCA). We explore how such
attacks can threaten isolation of any virtualized environments such as
cloud computing infrastructures. Finally, we study a set of different
applicable countermeasures for attack mitigation in cloud
infrastructures.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 17 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/publications/2018/08/17/AnnalsTelecommunications.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/publications/2018/08/17/AnnalsTelecommunications.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>publications</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Congratulations to Thomas for his habiliation</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;reconfiguration-dynamique-darchitectures-logicielles--des-métaclasses-aux--nuages-verts-&quot;&gt;Reconfiguration dynamique d’architectures logicielles : des métaclasses aux « nuages verts »&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/images-blog/Thomas-HDR1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;drawing&quot; width=&quot;355px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/images-blog/Thomas-HDR2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;drawing&quot; width=&quot;200px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cette habilitation à diriger des recherches présente une synthèse de
mes travaux ayant trait à la reconfiguration dynamique d’architectures
logicielles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;En première partie, je propose une analyse de l’adaptation dynamique
du logiciel avec la volonté de poser les concepts de base et
d’identifier les verrous à lever. Je motive l’intérêt de l’adaptation
dynamique et modélise son processus de développement. Je présente un
nombre de caractéristiques indispensables à l’adaptation dont la
réification et la modularité. Je traite alors l’adaptation dynamique
du logiciel comme un objet de première classe introduisant un
découplage spatio-temporel entre code métier et logique
d’adaptation. L’adaptation dynamique ne pouvant se faire au détriment
de la qualité du logiciel et de son intégrité, j’énumère un nombre de
propriétés indispensables à respecter, de pistes à étudier pour
réaliser à l’exécution ce processus d’adaptation du logiciel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;En deuxième partie, je présente ma contribution à la mise en œuvre de
l’adaptation dynamique pour les logiciels à base de composants. Dans
un premier temps, je propose un patron d’auto-administration pour les
architectures à composants, des langages dédiés pour la navigation et
la reconfiguration dans les architectures logicielles Fractal, un
framework pour faciliter la création d’applications sensibles au
contexte. Dans un second temps, je développe une approche multi-étape
pour des reconfigurations dynamiques fiables, qui contient à la fois
une partie prévention de fautes basée sur une analyse statique et une
partie tolérance aux fautes assurée par un moniteur
transactionnel. Cette approche s’appuie sur une spécification des
(re)configurations du modèle Fractal basée sur une logique du premier
ordre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;En troisième partie, je montre que la reconfiguration dynamique dans
les « architectures en nuages » (Cloud computing) peut apporter une
réponse à un enjeu sociétal important, à savoir les transitions
numérique et énergétique. Contrairement aux travaux actuels qui visent
à améliorer l’efficacité énergétique des centres de données en
proposant des solutions dans les couches basses du Cloud, je préconise
une approche d’éco-élasticité logicielle sur ses couches hautes. En
m’inspirant à la fois du concept d’innovation frugale (Jugaad) et du
mécanisme d’effacement de la consommation électrique, un certain
nombre d’artefacts originaux comme le Cloud SLA, l’effacement de la
consommation du logiciel, la virtualisation de l’énergie ou encore le
SaaS green energy-aware, sont suggérés pour diminuer l’empreinte
carbone des architectures en nuages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;En conclusion, je dresse un bilan final de ma contribution et présente
mes perspectives de recherche centrées d’abord sur une généralisation
de l’approche précédente à l’aide de méta-modèles, puis sur la
conception de micro-services « verts ».&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further information, please vise the &lt;a href=&quot;http://web.imt-atlantique.fr/x-info/ledoux/&quot;&gt;Thomas’s&lt;/a&gt; webpages.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/events/2018/07/17/HdR-Thomas.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/events/2018/07/17/HdR-Thomas.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>events</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Article accepted to GlobeCom 2018</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-tree-based-approach-to-locate-object-replicas-in-a-fog-storage-infrastructure&quot;&gt;A Tree-Based Approach to locate Object Replicas in a Fog Storage Infrastructure&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bastien Confais, Adrien Lebre, Benoit Parrein&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fog Computing infrastructures have been proposed as an alternative to
Cloud Computing to provide computing with low latency for the Internet
of Things (IoT). A few storage systems have been proposed to store
data in those infrastructures. Most of them are relying on a
Distributed Hash Table (DHT) which is not efficient because the node
storing the location of the data may be placed far away from the
object replicas. This leads to an access time of more than five
seconds in some network architectures. In this paper, we propose to
replace the DHT by a tree-based approach mapping the physical
topology. Servers look for the location of an object by requesting
successively their ancestors in the tree. Location records are also
relocated close to the object replicas not only to limit the network
traffic when requesting an object, but also to avoid an overload of
the root node. We also propose to modify the Dijkstra’s algorithm to
compute the tree used. Finally, we evaluate our approach using the
object store InterPlanetary FileSystem (IPFS) on Grid’5000 using both
a micro experiment with a simple network topology and a macro
experiment using the topology of the French National Research and
Education Network (RENATER). We show that the time to locate an object
in our approach is less than 15 ms on average which is around 20%
better than using a DHT.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further information on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://globecom2018.ieee-globecom.org&quot;&gt;GlobeCom 2018&lt;/a&gt; website.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 14 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/publications/2018/07/14/GlobeCom.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/publications/2018/07/14/GlobeCom.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>publications</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>SysMics project (Toward Systems Medicine based on Genomics) accepted</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;SysMics aims at federating the NExT scientific community toward a
common objective: anticipate the emergence of systems medicine by
co-developing 3 approaches in population-scale genomics: genotyping by
sequencing, cell-by-cell profiling and microbiome analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project is financed by the &lt;a href=&quot;http://next-isite.fr&quot;&gt;Nantes
excellency initiative in Medecine and Informatics (NeXT)&lt;/a&gt;. It will
start in the 3rd quarter of 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 07 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/projects/2018/07/07/Project-Accepted-SysMics.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/projects/2018/07/07/Project-Accepted-SysMics.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>projects</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Article accepted by IEEE TPDS</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;putting-the-next-500-vm-placement-algorithms-to-the-acid-test&quot;&gt;Putting the Next 500 VM Placement Algorithms to the Acid Test&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Adrien Lebre, Jonathan Pastor, Anthony Simonet, Mario Südholt&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most current infrastructures for cloud computing leverage static and
greedy policies for the placement of virtual machines. Such policies
impede the optimal allocation of resources from the infrastructure
provider viewpoint. Over the last decade, more dynamic and often more
efficient policies based, e.g., on consolidation and load balancing
techniques, have been developed. Due to the underlying complexity of
cloud infrastructures, these policies are evaluated either using
limited scale testbeds/in-vivo experiments or ad-hoc simulators. These
validation methodologies are unsatisfactory for two important reasons:
they (i) do not model precisely enough real production platforms
(size, workload variations, failure, etc.) and (ii) do not enable the
fair comparison of different approaches. More generally, new placement
algorithms are thus continuously being proposed without actually
identifying their benefits with respect to the state of the art.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this article, we show how VMPlaceS, a dedicated simulation
framework enables researchers (i) to study and compare VM placement
algorithms from the infrastructure perspective, (ii) to detect
possible limitations at large scale and (iii) to easily investigate
different design choices. Built on top of the SimGrid simulation
platform, VMPlaceS provides programming support to ease the
implementation of placement algorithms and runtime support dedicated
to load injection and execution trace analysis. To illustrate the
relevance of VMPlaceS, we first discuss a few experiments that enabled
us to study in details three well known VM placement
strategies. Diving into details, we also identify several
modifications that can significantly increase their performance in
terms of reactivity. Second, we complete this overall presentation of
VMPlaceS by focusing on the energy efficiency of the well-know FFD
strategy. We believe that VMPlaceS will allow researchers to validate
the benefits of new placement algorithms, thus accelerating placement
research and favouring the transfer of results to IaaS production
platforms.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/publications/2018/06/15/One-paper-Accepted-By-IEEE-TPDS.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/publications/2018/06/15/One-paper-Accepted-By-IEEE-TPDS.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>publications</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
